Bloch, Edward J.; Papers apap115
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Edward J. Bloch Papers
1931-2001
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Bloch, Edward J.
apap115
5.41 cubic ft.
This collection contains the papers of Edward J. Bloch (1924-2014), a native of New York who served in the military between 1943 and 1946 with assignments in Okinawa during World War II and post-war North China, taught science in Istanbul, Turkey (1947-1950), and dedicated the majority of his career to labor concerns as a representative for the labor union United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (1950-1984). Edward Bloch also served as President of the Labor Action Coalition of New York (1975 to the late 1990s), Director of the Interfaith Impact for the New York State Council of Churches (1987-1995), and ran unsuccessfully for two different congressional district seats (1984, 1986, 1995-1996). Among the many honors Bloch received during his lifetime is the Purple Heart, which he was awarded for his actions during World War II.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Edward J. Bloch in May 2001.
Biographical Sketch
Edward James Bloch (Block) was born to Henry, a New York attorney, and Sylvia Bloch, in New York City on April 17, 1924.
Known as either Ed or Jim to his family and friends, he lived in Scarsdale, New York until he attended college. At the age of 17, Bloch entered the U.S. Marine Corps V-12 program, which encouraged college students to train for military service. Simultaneously attending Williams College in Williamstown, Massachusetts, Private Bloch rose to Lieutenant Bloch in the U.S. Marine Corps Reserves. Leaving Williams College between 1942 and 1943, he entered Dartmouth in Hanover, New Hampshire, to continue the V-12 program.
Military service between 1943 and 1946 interrupted his academic career. During World War II, he was stationed in San Francisco, California; Camp Lejeune, North Carolina; Okinawa; and North China. Rising from a 2nd Lieutenant to a 1st Lieutenant, Bloch became Rifle Platoon Leader in the "L" Company, 3rd Battalion, 7th Marines. While in Okinawa in 1945, he was shot in the right arm and leg. Months later, on September 30, Bloch's new assignment was the post-war occupation of North China. Interviewed years later, he recalled the atrocities committed against civilians here by a combined force of Marines and Japanese soldiers, who were ordered to prevent a further Communist infiltration in certain locations of North China. One such incident included taking part in the shooting of civilians under orders from a Japanese officer (Bloch, Edward J..Courage Coward Courage!! undated. p. 59-62. Oversize Box 1, Folder 15). For his actions in World War II, Bloch was awarded a Bronze Star and the Purple Heart.
Finished with his military career, Bloch returned to Williams College, receiving a B.A. in 1946. The following year, he attended the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy and obtained a M.A. From 1947 to 1949, Bloch taught science and coached basketball and wrestling at Robert College in Istanbul, Turkey. During this period, he also acted as a foreign correspondent for The Christian Science Monitor.
By 1950, the soldier turned teacher came home. Between 1950 and 1984, Edward Bloch dedicated his time to labor concerns and the labor union, United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE). Beginning as a chief steward and rising to a field organizer and international representative, Bloch collectively bargained contracts with companies, such as General Electric, Westinghouse, and ExCello. He helped organize the Local 332 branch of the UE just outside Albany, New York. For 17 years, he served as an international representative for the UE and worked in New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Maryland, Vermont, and South Carolina.
From 1975 to the late 1990s, Edward Bloch served as President of the Labor Action Coalition of New York. In this position he coordinated the political action of numerous local unions, fought to save jobs and obtain employee benefits. Bloch also worked with the Labor/Religion Coalition of the Capital District for similar means.
In 1984 and 1986, Bloch ran two campaigns for New York State's 24th Congressional District seat. As a Democrat in 1984 and 1986, he faced Republican Gerald Solomon and lost both times. In 1995-1996, Bloch ran as an Independent candidate for the 21st Congressional District seat and again failed in his bid for election.
Beside his political ambitions, Bloch volunteered much of his time in the late 1980s and 1990s to interfaith organizations. Between 1987 and 1995, he served as Director of the Interfaith Impact for the New York State Council of Churches. As director, Bloch represented a collection of religious groups determined to translate their religious and moral beliefs into mostly legislative action. After eight years, Bloch left Interfaith Impact for the Interfaith Alliance (TIANYS). The Interfaith Alliance was similar to the Interfaith Impact, demanding changes in public policy based on religious understanding.
Throughout his life, Edward J. Bloch developed his own religious and moral understanding or philosophy of life. Fearing the cruelty of anti-Semitism in America after the first World War, Bloch's parents, both of the Jewish faith, tried to hide his religious identity. Seeing the horrors of World War II in combat and in the occupation of China, he changed his allegiance from capitalism to socialism in the post-war period. During the Vietnam War, he protested U.S. military intervention in Southeast Asia through Veterans for Peace in Vietnam. As a labor leader, he dedicated more than 30 years to workers through the UE, even being investigated by the FBI for ties to Communism in his union. Finally, while observing Presbyterian values and beliefs, he still recognized the need for interfaith organizations.
Bloch's family is mentioned frequently in his personal papers. They include his second wife, Naomi Finkelstein, daughter Rebecca, and his three children from a previous marriage, Linda, Alan, and Susan. Other key figures mentioned in the collection are Lawrence Wittner, retired professor of history at the University at Albany, the late Joe Powers, former Chair of the Capital District Labor Religion Coalition, former Governor Mario Cuomo, and folk singer Pete Seeger (Bloch, Edward J..Courage Coward Courage!! undated. p. 59-62. Oversize Box 1, Folder 15). Bloch passed away on August 24, 2014. He was survived by his wife Naomi, children, five grandchildren and two great-grandchildren.
Scope and Contents
The collected papers of Edward J. Bloch detail his early life, his military service in the Marine Corps during World War II, his three years in Turkey teaching biology, leadership in the UE, the Labor Action Coalition, the Capital Labor Religion Coalition, Interfaith Impact, Interfaith Alliance, three unsuccessful campaigns for Congress, and personal papers and correspondence.
Correspondence and creative writing make up the majority of Bloch's papers. His letters are particularly voluminous between 1944 and 1946, when he served in Okinawa and China as a Marine. During this time span, he wrote mostly to his parents and brother, Henry, concerning the war, his current positions in Asia, and on other personal matters. His father replied specifically with news from the home front concerning the war and politics. Other letters in the collection span his career in the UE, Congressional campaign runs, and varied personal subjects. Beside correspondence, Bloch wrote poetry, plays, essays, and other literature. These writings begin in the published version of his very early poetry, Verses(1931).
Of the records kept on the UE and Bloch's other union work, those files on General Electric and FBI files on Bloch and the UE stand out above the rest. Beside these records, only the 1984, 1986, and 1995-1996 congressional election folders have a great deal of substance. Election letters, news clippings, press releases, notes, speeches, pamphlets, stickers, a poster, buttons, photos, newsletters, and position statements, are all included in these files.
Many files were originally interspersed in various folders of the collection, leaving some half-written letters, notes detached from their original position, and copies of newspaper articles with missing sections or words. Most of the handwritten notes lack dates and are difficult to decipher. Likewise, many newspaper clippings lack dates and do not specifically mention Edward Bloch.
Some of the Capital District Labor Religion Coalition papers from 1981-1985 were created by former co-chair, Lawrence Wittner, a professor of history at the University at Albany. For more information on Wittner, consult the Lawrence Wittner (APAP-100) collection. The papers of Libby Post (APAP-045) include materials created during the 1984 and 1986 campaigns to defeat Gerald Solomon. Post served as Bloch's Press Secretary. For additional labor collections in the Department, see the online Labor subject guide at http://library.albany.edu/speccoll/conservation.htm. For other related collections, consult the Archives of Public Affairs and Policy in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archvies.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1: Early Life, 1931-1943, .33 cubic ft.
Series 2: World War II, 1942-1946, 1972, 1996, .62 cubic ft.
Series 3: Istanbul, Turkey, 1947-1950, .37 cubic ft.
Series 4: United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America, 1949-2001, .53 cubic ft.
Series 5: Labor Action Coalition of New York, 1977-1985, .53 cubic ft.
Series 6: Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition, 1981-1996, .33 cubic ft.
Series 7: Congressional Campaigns, 1982-1996, .50 cubic ft.
Series 8: Interfaith Impact and Interfaith Alliance, 1990-2000, .33 cubic ft.
Series 9: Personal Correspondence and Papers, 1939-2001, .53 cubic ft.
All series are arranged alphabetically with the exception of Series 6, which is arranged by subject. Series 7 is organized alphabetically by campaign.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Public Servants; Military and Armed Conflict; Labor; Albany, New York; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Japan--Okinawa Island; New York (State)--Politics and government; Correspondence; Essays; Newsletters; Bloch, Edward J.; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America; Interfaith Alliance
- Early Life, 1931-1943; Undated; 1; 0.33 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records dating from 1931 to 1943. It includes files on Ed Bloch's high school and college related activities, correspondence, news clippings, poetry, essays, short stories, papers, and miscellaneous files.
  - Correspondence, 1936-1943 (Box 1 (1-Early Life), Folder 1)
  - Diary Sheet and Record Card, 1937-1938 (Box 1 (1-Early Life), Folder 2)
  - Essays, Stories, and Papers, 1939-1943; Undated (Box 1 (1-Early Life), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1941-1943 (Box 1 (1-Early Life), Folder 4)
  - Poetry, 1931-1940 (Box 1 (1-Early Life), Folder 5)
  - Williams College Materials, 1941-1943; Undated (Box 1 (1-Early Life), Folder 6)
- World War II, 1942-1946; 1972; 1996; Undated; 2; 0.62 cubic ft.
  This series focuses on Ed Bloch's military involvement during World War II, with material dating from 1942 to 1972. It includes files on World War II related activities, correspondence, news clippings, poetry, essays, short stories, papers, and miscellaneous files. Most of the material comes from the 1940s, with articles recalling Bloch's World War II experiences written in the 1970s and a book commemorating the 1996 reunion of the Special Officer Candidate School which Bloch attended.
  - Brochure, "Information for Christian Scientists", Undated (Box 1(continued) (2-World War II), Folder 7)
  - Bulletin for Concerned Asian Scholars and Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 11-12)
  - Correspondence, 1946; Undated (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 13)
  - Essays, Stories, Papers, 1945-1946 (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 14)
  - News Clippings about Bloch, 1944-1946 (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 15)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 16)
  - Poetry, 1944-1946 (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 17)
  - Sketch of Ed Bloch, Undated (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 18)
  - Telegrams, 1942 (Box 1 (2-World War II), Folder 19)
  - Candidates Class for Commission, 1942 (Box 2 (2-World War II), Folder 1)
  - Essay, 1945 (Box 2 (2-World War II), Folder 2)
  - Photographs, ca. 1943-1946 (Box 2 (2-World War II), Folder 3)
  - Poetry, 1931-1940 (Box 2 (2-World War II), Folder 4)
  - Winning of the War in Europe and the Pacific, 1943-1945 (Box 2 (2-World War II), Folder 5)
  - Book, The SOCs [SOCs= Special Officer Candidate School], 1996 (Oversized 1)
- Departments and Committees, 1947-1950; 3; 0.37 cubic ft.
  This series is comprised of records dating from 1947 to 1950 when Ed Bloch taught biology in Istanbul, Turkey and was a foreign correspondent for The Christian Science Monitor. It includes files on early Cold War related activities, correspondence, Turkish news clippings, articles written for The Christian Science Monitor, essays, short stories, and papers.
  - The Christian Science Monitor, 1947-1949 (Box 1 (3-Departments and Committees), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 1 (3-Departments and Committees), Folder 2)
  - Essays, Stories, Papers, 1947-1950 (Box 1 (3-Departments and Committees), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1949 (Box 1 (3-Departments and Committees), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2 (3-Departments and Committees), Folder 1)
- United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America, 1949-2001; Undated; 4; 0.53 cubic ft.
  This series documents Ed Bloch's career as a field organizer and international representative for the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America from 1950 to 1984. The files in this series date from 1949 to 2001 and include labor related activities, correspondence, news clippings, handwritten notes and rough drafts, newsletters, files related to the UE Local 332 labor organization, General Electric related files, FBI documents, and miscellaneous papers.
  - Articles, Essays, and Papers, 1975-1986; Undated (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 1)
  - Book, Them and us: Struggles of a Rank File Union, by J. J. Matles and J. Higgins, Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall Inc., 1974 (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1995 (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with FBI and Navy, 1983 (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 4)
  - FBI Files, 1950-1960 (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 5)
  - Fliers and Event Announcements, 1985; Undated (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 6)
  - General Electric, 1981-1999; Undated (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 7)
  - Local 332 Ballots, 1979-1998 (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 8)
  - Meeting Minutes and Notices, 1987-1993 (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, 1949-1988 (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 10)
  - Newsletters, UE Local #332, 1992-2001 (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 11)
  - Rough Drafts and Notes, 1979-1983 (Box 1 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 12)
  - General Electric, UE Local 332, News Announcements, Meeting Synopsis, 1974-1993 (Box 2 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 1)
  - General Electric, 1976-1991 (Box 2 (4-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of Am), Folder 2)
- Labor Action Coalition of New York, 1977-1985; Undated; 5; 0.53 cubic ft.
  This series contains records dating from 1977 to 1985. It includes correspondence, newsletters, press releases, news clippings, reports, and speeches.
  - Agendas for Meetings, 1977-1982 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 1)
  - Annual Legislative Conference Registration Lists, 1978-1983 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1978-1983 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 3)
  - By-laws, 1978 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 5)
  - Executive Board Lists, 1978-1979; Undated (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 6)
  - Fliers and Brochures, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 7)
  - Jobs Rally, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 8)
  - Litigation, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 9)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1978-1983 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 10)
  - News Clippings, 1982-1983 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 11)
  - Newsletters and Press Releases, 1979-1983 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 12)
  - Notes and Drafts, Undated (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 13)
  - Papers and Reports (Non Labor Action Coliation), 1977-1982; Undated (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 14)
  - Payment of Dues Lists, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 15)
  - Poems and Songs, Undated (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 16)
  - Reports and Speeches, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 17)
  - State Assembly Member and Witness Lists, 1980; Undated (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 18)
  - State of New York 1981-1982 Regular Sessions in Assembly (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 19)
  - Union/Community Committee for Solidarity, 1982; Undated (Box 1 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 20)
  - Peoples Power Coalition, 1979; 1981 (Box 2 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 1)
  - Notes and Drafts, Undated (Box 2 (5-Labor Action Coalition of New York), Folder 2)
- Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition, 1981-1996; Undated; 6; 0.33 cubic ft.
  Arranged by subject.
  This series is a collection of records dated from 1981-1996. The correspondence, meeting agendas and minutes, news clippings, newsletters, and press releases from 1981 to 1985, were collected by Lawrence Wittner when he was Co-Chair and given to Ed Bloch. Similar items from 1985 to 1996 were collected by Ed Bloch as executive secretary of the organization.
  - Correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 1)
  - Fliers, Event Announcements, 1982; Undated (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 2)
  - Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1982-1984 (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, Articles, 1981-1983; Undated (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 4)
  - Newsletters, 1981-1983 (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 5)
  - Press Releases, 1983; Undated (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 6)
  - Reports of New York State Labor Religion Commission, 1982-1983 (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 7)
  - State of New York 1981-1982 Regular Sessions in Assembly (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 8)
  - Reports, Summaries, and Resolutions, 1982-1983; Undated (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 9)
  - AFL-CIO "Current Developments", 1987 (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 10)
  - AFL-CIO Daily Labor Report, 1987 (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 11)
  - By-laws, 1995 (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1996; Undated (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 13)
  - Fliers, Applications, 1985-1998; Undated (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 14)
  - Mailing Lists, 1987-1995; Undated (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 15)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1985-1995 (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 16)
  - News Clippings, 1987-1994 (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 17)
  - Press Releases, 1986-1988 (Box 1 (6-Capital District Labor/Religion Coalition), Folder 18)
- Congressional Campaigns, 1982-1996; Undated; 7; 0.50 cubic ft.
  Arranged alphabetically by campaign.
  This series contains records dating from 1982 to 1996, covering Ed Bloch's three unsuccessful bids for Congress. It includes files on campaign related activities, correspondence, news clippings, press releases, position statements, newsletters, photographs, notes, pamphlets, stickers, posters, buttons, benefit and fundraiser ads and invitations.
  - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 1)
  - Congressional Voting Record, 1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 2)
  - County Enrollments and Committee Lists, 1983-1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 3)
  - Expenditures, 1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 4)
  - Fliers, Events Announcements, 1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 5)
  - The Freeze Economy, 1982 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 6)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 7)
  - News Clippings, 1982-1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 8)
  - Newsletters, 1983-1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 9)
  - Political Action Committee Kit and Cover Letter, 1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 11)
  - Position Statements, 1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 12)
  - Press Releases, Public Relations, 1983-1984 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 13)
  - ""The 1984 Campaign of Ed Bloch,"" (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 14)
  - Account Information, 1990 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1988 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 16)
  - Fliers, Event Announcements, 1986 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 17)
  - Meeting, 1986 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 18)
  - News Clippings, 1985-1988 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 19)
  - Newsletters, 1985-1986 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 20)
  - Press Releases, 1986 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 21)
  - Position Statements and Speeches, 1985-1986 (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 22)
  - Various Lists of Campaign Contributors, 1986-1987; Undated (Box 1 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 2 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 1)
  - Mailing Lists, 1996 (Box 2 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1994-1996 (Box 2 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 3)
  - Position Statements, 1995-1996 (Box 2 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 4)
  - Resume, 1996 (Box 2 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 5)
  - Speeches, 1995-1996 (Box 2 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Maps, and Election Tallies, Undated (Box 2 (7-Congressional Campaigns), Folder 7)